Guide to the Tom Carey papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tom Carey papers
1890-2009
1960-2009
YCAL MSS 1210
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.0
(18 boxes)
This collection contains writings, photographs, correspondence, journals and other material created by writer, poet, and vicar, Tom Carey. Correspondence and journals contain content related to writers and artists associated with the first and second generations of the New York School, including James Schuyler, Eileen Myles, and John Ashbery.
Carey, Tom
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 12 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 15-16 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Tom Carey
Thomas (Tom) Carey is a writer, poet, and vicar in the Church of the Epiphany in Los Angeles, California. Carey was born in 1951 in Santa Monica, California and is of English and German descent. He graduated from Columbia University with a degree in Spanish and studied theology at Church Divinity School of the Pacific. His father and grandfathers were western movie actors, and Carey himself studied acting with Jack Garfein and Stella Adler. In the 1970s and 80s Carey fronted for the punk rock band, The Beeks, and was a literary assistant to James Schuyler as well as John Ashbery. Carey became a Franciscan brother in 1988 and ran The Bushwick Play Project and taught poetry in New York City public schools for ten years. Carey's poetry has been published in various anthologies, magazines and journals. His book of poems, titled Desire, (Painted Leaf Press, 1997) was a Lambda Literary Award finalist.
Arrangement
Arranged into seven series: I. Correspondence, circa 1960s-2000s. II. Journals, 1964-2007. III. Writings, circa 1960s-1990s. IV. Personal papers, circa 1960s-2000s. V. Photographs, circa 1890s-2000s. VI. Audiovisual materials, 1978-1992. VII. James Schuyler material, circa 1980s-2000s
Scope and Contents
This collection contains writings, photographs, correspondence, journals and other material created by writer, poet, and vicar, Tom Carey. Correspondence and journals contain content related to writers and artists associated with the first and second generations of the New York School, including James Schuyler, Eileen Myles, and John Ashbery.
American poetry -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Correspondence; Authors, American -- Archives; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials; LGBTQ resource; Schuyler, James; Myles, Eileen, 1949-; Ashbery, John, 1927-2017
- Correspondence, circa 1960s-2000s; Series I
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is organized alphabetically by sender, with unidentified and miscellaneous correspondence located at the end of the series.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence received by Tom Carey between the 1960s and 2000s. Also includes unsent letters written by Carey.
  - Bathurst, Bill, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Brainard, Joe, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Brodey, Jim, 1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Berrigan, Ted, undated (Box 1)
  - Carey family, 1970s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Corbett, Bill, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Corn, Alfred, 1983-1992 (Box 1)
  - Dlugos, Tim, 1990; undated (Box 1)
  - Dorn, Edward, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Engler, Maurice, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Fedorko, Gene [G.F.], 1983 (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, Steve, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Hannah, Duncan, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Howard, Richard, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Hurlbert, David, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Huston, Bo, circa 1980s (Box 2)
  - Kernan, Nathan, circa 1990s (Box 2)
  - Latsky, Eric, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Martin, Tandy, 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
  - McCourt, James, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 2)
    Includes a playscript for Intolerance
  - Milton, Adrian, 1980s-1990s (Box 2)
  - Moshontz, Ron, 1976; 1988 (Box 2)
  - Myles, Eileen, circa 1980s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Contains writing by Myles including the manuscript for Chelsea Girls and The Inferno.
  - Notley, Alice, circa 1980s (Box 3)
  - Palmer, Liz, 1979-1986 (Box 3)
  - Park, Darragh, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Poetry project and poetry festival, 1980; 1989 (Box 3)
  - Rowley, Fitch, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Schneeman, Elio, 1982-1992 (Box 3)
  - Schuyler, James, circa 1970s-1991; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Trinidad, David, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 4)
  - Unsent correspondence by Tom Carey, circa 1960s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Unidentified and miscellaneous correspondence, circa 1960s-1990s; 8 folders (Box 4–5)
- Journals, 1964-2007; Series II
  Journals consist of writing by Carey between the 1960s and 2000s.
  Journals are organized chronologically into two sequences of numbered and unnumbered journals. Undated journals are located at the end of the series.
  - Travel journal, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Journal, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Diary, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Dream notebook, circa 1980s (Box 6)
  - Journal, circa 1980s (Box 6)
  - Day planner, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Day planner, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Day planner, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Journal, vol. I, 1973-1977 (Box 6)
  - Journal, vol. II, 1977-1980 (Box 6)
  - Journal, vol. III, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Journal, vol. IV, 1981-1984 (Box 7)
  - Journal, vol. V, 1986-1988 (Box 7)
  - Journal, vol. VI, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
  - Journal, vol. VII, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - Journal, vol. VIII, 1993-1995 (Box 7)
  - Journal., vol. IX, 1995-1997 (Box 7)
  - Journal, vol. X, 1998-2001 (Box 8)
  - Journal, vol. XI, 2001-2004 (Box 8)
  - Journal, vol. XII, 2004-2007 (Box 8)
  - Notebooks, undated; 4 folders (Box 8)
- Writings, circa 1960s-1990s; Series III
  Includes poetry and playscripts by Carey, as well as other writers.
  Material is arranged chronologically, with undated materials located at the end of the series.
  - Poetry, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 9)
  - Writing, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 9)
  - Writing and poetry, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 9)
  - Clear the Range by Ted Berrigan, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Play scripts and poetry, circa 1980s-1990s, undated (Box 9)
  - The Paul Clown Show playscript, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Book cover mock-up for Desire, 1997 (Box 18)
  - Best Friends screenplay, undated (Box 9)
  - Intolerance playscript, undated (Box 10)
  - Screenplay, undated (Box 10)
- Personal papers, circa 1960s-2000s; Series IV
  Includes artwork and notes created by Carey, as well as material related to Carey's band, The Beeks.
  - Notes and personal material, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 10)
  - The Beeks material, circa 1960s-1980s; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Address book, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Note to archivists, undated (Box 11)
  - Artwork, undated; 2 folders (Box 11, Box 18)
  - Exhibition postcards, undated (Box 11)
- Photographs, circa 1890s-2000s; Series V
  Includes prints and negatives of photographs taken by Carey, as well as portraits of Carey and his friends and family.
  Material is arranged in its received order.
  - Childhood and family photographs, circa 1890s-1961 (Box 11)
  - Photographs (prints and negatives), circa 1960s-2000s; 4 folders (Box 11)
  - CD-ROM, 2004; 1 (Box 12)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    Photographs on the CD are represented as both prints and negatives in Box 11.
  - Photographs (prints and negatives), circa 1960s-1990s; 6 folders (Box 13)
  - Photographs (prints and negatives), circa 1960s-1990s; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Tom Carey acting head shots, circa 1970s-1980s; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Photographs (prints and negatives), circa 1970s-2000s (Box 18)
- Audiovisual materials, 1978-1992; Series VI
  Material is arranged by format.
  Audiovisual material including audiocassettes, a VHS tape and a reel-to-reel audiotape.
  - James Schuyler memorial VHS tape, 1992; 1 (Box 15)
  - The Morning of the Poem, James Schuyler, 1981 September 9; 1 (Box 15)
  - The Morning of the Poem, James Schuyler, 1982; 1 (Box 15)
  - Phone tape, 1985 September; 1 (Box 15)
  - James Schuyler and John Ashbery, Poetry Center NYC, 1989 November 20; 1 (Box 15)
  - James Schuyler: Hymn to Life and other poems, 1986 November 9; 1 (Box 15)
  - James Schuyler memorial and Hymn to Life, The Poetry Project, tape 1 of 2, 1992 February 26; 1 (Box 15)
  - James Schuyler memorial and Hymn to Life, The Poetry Project, tape 2 of 2, 1992 February 26; 1 (Box 15)
  - James Schuyler at SFAI, 1989 February 10; 1 (Box 15)
  - James Schuyler for Darragh Park from Tom Oppenheim, NYU, 1991 February 6; 1 (Box 15)
  - Morning of the Poem, 1978-1993; 1 (Box 15)
  - Hymn to Life, undated; 1 (Box 15)
  - James Schuyler Hymn to Life and other poems, flawed version, 1986 November 9; 1 (Box 15)
  - Tom Carey CBGBs, 1978; 1 (Box 15)
  - The Beeks, undated; 1 (Box 15)
  - Unlabeled cassette, undated; 1 (Box 15)
  - Unlabeled audiotape reel, undated; 1 (Box 16)
- James Schuyler material, circa 1980s-2000s; Series VII
  Includes material relating to James Schuyler, including poetry and correspondence by Schuyler, as well as documents relating to his estate. Other material relating to Schuyler can be found in additional series in the collection.
  - Poetry, correspondence, legal documents, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 17)
  - The selected art writings of James Schuyler, circa 1990s; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Memorial material, 1991 (Box 17)
  - Memorial guestbook, 1991 (Box 17)
  - Other Flowers: The Uncollected Poems of James Schuyler, 2006; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Photograph of Schuyler, undated (Box 17)
  - Schuyler poetry, undated (Box 17)